Stanford University.
Quick question.
One thing that I'm confused about is
back vacuum energy.
I know you said when you get to Planck
scale it it explodes.
What my question in particular does
electron positron positron pair
production and annihilation actually
occur or is that excluded by
uh Actually occur means what? That you
can actually see out of the vacuum
electrons and positrons coming out? Due
to let's say the vacuum measured vacuum
density if that would be that a fair
measure.
Electron positron
virtual pair production
virtual
pairs do contribute to the vacuum
energy.
That doesn't mean
that you should see electron positron
pairs popping out of nowhere. It does
not mean that.
It mean
It means they pop out and go back
in a very short time subject to the
uncertainty principle.
Uh
so it's
quantum fluctuation and not real genuine
particles being produced.
It's much like the zero point energy of
a harmonic oscillator.
Classically the harmonic oscillator just
sits still at the bottom of its
potential well.
Quantum mechanically it cannot both sit
still and be at the quantum bottom of
the potential.
There's competition
and uh it's resolved by a little bit of
quantum fluctuation. That quantum
fluctuation has energy. How much is it?
A half H bar omega.
Okay? It's always there. Can't get rid
of it. It's the least energy that the
oscillator can have.
And the same
course that doesn't mean looking at the
oscillator
most quantum oscillators are too small
to see.
Um
It is the ground state and as the ground
state it means it's the state in which
nothing is happening to the extent that
nothing can happen.
Same is true with electron positron
pairs. Same is true with virtual
photons.
Um and in fact it's a closely related
phenomenon.
The
electromagnetic field for example in a
cavity. Electromagnetic field in a
cavity is just a collection of harmonic
oscillators.
Each oscillator has a little bit of zero
point energy.
Add them all up.
You call that the vacuum energy.
Well uh
I was saving that for a little bit later
but uh yeah.
Uh because it plays an important role in
cosmology.
Okay. Are you also going to
talk again about the 120 orders of
magnitude? No, I think I won't spend a
lot of time on that. I'll mention it but
um
uh
No, I thought tonight in any case we
mainly concentrate on cosmic horizons.
What a horizon is, why there are
horizons.
And um
and a little bit about
cosmology the equations of cosmology
how they lead to an accelerated
expanding universe and why the
accelerated expanding universe has event
horizons.
I thought that would be a good thing to
do tonight.
Since we've spent a lot of time learning
about what a horizon is. We're not quite
finished learning what a horizon is.
We have 4 minutes.
I was going to say you you mentioned
last week I guess it was the
ultraviolet and infrared
relationship
and you said you were going to be
getting to that is that tonight or
Well, we can talk about it. All right.
That's a good maybe we'll start with
that.
Um
Maybe. It's not really on my list of
things to do tonight. Maybe we'll get to
it though if I run out of things.
Wait 3 minutes and
sit think I have a question I
related to the question back there about
vacuum energy and
if in the vacuum there is a positive
energy density
why wouldn't that have some kind of
refractive effect on Refractive?
Optically refractive effect.
What is refractive? Refractive
Remind me which is refraction reflection
Is that the speed of light? Speed of
light would the speed of light for
example would be ever so slightly less
than a quantum vacuum as opposed to free
space.
Um
The vacuum energy it's a good question.
It's a good question.
Most energy
that you think about
if you have that energy present
it creates a situation
where the world is not Lorentz
invariant. I don't mean that the theory
is not Lorentz invariant. I mean that
the configuration of the world is not
Lorentz invariant. What does it mean?
What what what exactly does that mean?
Let's first talk about something
simpler.
Translation invariance. Every place is
like every other place, right? No, it's
not true. Stanford University is not
like Berkeley.
Uh the Earth is not like the Sun and
it's certainly not like interstellar
space.
So what do we mean when we say the world
has translation invariance?
We don't mean
that the configuration of the world
every place looks the same.
Uh
We mean if we took the whole thing and
moved it it would look the same it would
look the same but moving it means moving
us, moving Berkeley, moving everything
else.
Now in the same way
uh you talk about Lorentz invariance.
Is the world Lorentz invariant?
No.
Tell you why in a minute. Are the
equations of physics Lorentz invariant?
Yes.
So what does it mean for the world not
to be Lorentz invariant?
Well, it means that for whatever reason
the stuff in the universe
uh does not look the same from every
frame of reference.
If I were to whiz by you at a thousand
miles a second you would look different
to me than than if I was standing still.
So stuff in the world stuff in the world
breaks the symmetries that we talk
about.
They
create special locations.
They they create
special directions.
The equations of physics are supposed to
be rotationally invariant that means the
same no matter how we rotate. True
enough the equations of physics are
rotationally invariant but is this room
rotationally invariant? Certainly not.
If I look that way I see you. If I look
that way I see something else.
So the presence of stuff breaks
symmetries. And presence of stuff breaks
Lorentz invariance. The world is not
Lorentz invariant by virtue of the fact
that the stuff in it.
Now
most of the times the stuff energy and
so forth as I said is not Lorentz
invariant.
And the result of that
is in particular a result on the motion
of light waves.
Light waves moving through materials
have different velocity than they have
moving through empty space.
The rule about the speed of light is
that light always travels with the same
velocity in empty space but that's
another way of saying that empty space
is Lorentz invariant. Empty space is
Lorentz invariant. Empty space is
translation invariant. It's rotation
invariant. Empty space is
is
has no preferred frames of reference.
And
the statement that light always travels
with the same velocity is a statement
about a Lorentz invariant world where
there is no preferred frame of
reference. When there's a preferred
frame of reference due to the presence
of material
light can travel at any velocity lower
than the speed of light than the usual
speed of light.
Now
vacuum energy is very special.
Vacuum energy is the one exceptional
situation
where the presence of that energy is
Lorentz invariant. Does not pick out a
reference frame.
If you weren't here and the room wasn't
here and I was in absolutely empty space
nevertheless there would be vacuum
energy in this room.
The vacuum energy has a certain value
whatever it's numerical value is a
certain number of joules per
per cubic meter very very tiny.
Um but nevertheless finite.
And so you might think well that's like
a material being here. It's like a stuff
being here and a stuff being here would
define a frame of reference
where the stuff would be at rest. Vacuum
energy is very special that way.
It does not define a frame of reference.
I could detect
the vacuum energy with a vacuum energy
detector. I won't tell you how to build
one. I'll tell you how to build one a
little while.
It's
we'll talk about how you build a vacuum
energy detector.
Okay?
I could detect the vacuum energy and see
how much is here. I would get some
number.
I would then go whizzing by as fast as I
can go and do the same experiment.
If it was ordinary material, I would
discover that the energy changes. The
energy that material changes with my
velocity.
In particular,
um
if I whizz past a gas,
then of course, the gas looks higher
energy. Why? Because all the molecules
appear to be moving past me.
Vacuum energy is the one special case
where my vacuum energy detector will
give the same answer no matter how I'm
moving.
So, vacuum energy is the special case
where its presence does not pick out a
special frame of reference, does not
violate Lorentz invariance, and it's a
special case where light will move with
the speed of light independently of the
observer.
Now, moving with the speed of light
means something. It means when the light
ray passes you,
passes right in front of your nose and
you have your clocks and your detectors
locally, right near you, you measure the
same velocity of light.
Because of the expansion of the universe
and so forth, it becomes a more
problematic question of whether light
moves relative to us far, far away when
the light is far away from us,
does it move with the speed of light?
And we're going to talk about that.
Uh the answer is no, not in general.
It moves relative to local observers
where that light is passing by them with
the same speed of light, but
it doesn't necessarily move relative to
us with the speed of light.
Move faster or slower?
In this discussion, is
vacuum energy synonymous with the
cosmological Yes, absolutely. And uh
All right, so let's begin there. Why
don't we begin there?
Um if we take the universe and fill it
with full of particles,
then let's say ordinary particles,
protons,
fill it up. I don't mean fill it up so
that every proton is against every other
proton. I just mean, you know, create
some uniform density of protons.
And of course, the universe is something
like that. It's not so different.
There's a more or less uniform
uh energy density
throughout all of space. It tends to be
clustered into stars and stuff like
that, but on scales bigger than
superclusters of galaxies,
um it's, you know, homogeneously
distributed, rather diffuse.
Something, if I remember, something like
about 50 protons per cubic meter on the
average.
Okay?
Uh
and there's some energy density. Let's
give that energy density a name.
Standard terminology for a density is
rho.
And now that could stand for the mass
density, mass and energy being the same
thing.
All right, so that's the mass density.
That's consistent of a bunch of
particles.
Now, what happens, and it's the it's the
number of particles
per unit volume
or the number of particles times the
mass of each particle divided by a
volume of space. Take a volume of space,
the density of energy
is the mass of each particle. Let's
suppose there's only one kind of
particle.
The particles are standing still.
They're not photons. Let's not get
involved all with photons right now.
They're just protons standing still,
protons, neutrons, electrons, atoms.
The mass of an individual particle
times the number of particles in a
volume divided by the volume, that's the
that's the density.
Now, what happens to that density as the
universe begins to expand?
Well, the number of particles doesn't
change.
At least not if they're ordinary
particles.
The number of particles doesn't change.
Their mass doesn't change. What does
change is the volume of the region of
space occupied by those particles.
So, we take some particles that started
out in a region of space a square on a
side uh 100 light years
on a side, 100 light years, 100 light
years the other way, too.
It has a volume of a million cubic light
me light years,
which is some number in cubic meters.
That's the volume that goes in here.
The number of particles stays the same.
And now the universe expands, everything
expands with it on sufficiently big
scales, the volume of space, let's say,
over some period of time doubles.
When the volume of space doubles,
what
I'm sorry. I meant the radius of the I
didn't mean the volume.
When the radius
of this cube, the linear dimension of
the cube doubles, what happens to the
density?
Well,
when the radius doubles, the volume gets
multiplied by eight and the density
becomes 1/8 of what it started.
Okay?
So, ordinary material has the behavior,
and this is true for
photons, for anything. Not this exact
formula is a little bit different for
photons, but the general rule is that as
the universe expands, the energy density
dilutes.
All right? It decreases. The density of
energy decreases just because everything
separates.
Again, vacuum energy is the exception.
Vacuum energy is the exception.
Vacuum energy has the property vacuum
energy density. Vacuum energy density
has the property
that as the universe expands, as the
volume of space expands,
the amount of the density of energy does
not change. The density,
not the amount in the bo- in the box,
but the amount per cubic meter always
stays the same.
If the universe were to expand by a
factor of 100 in every direction,
uh the volume of a region of space would
go up by a million.
Nevertheless, the density of vacuum
energy in this room would stay exactly
the same. So, it's a property of empty
space which just doesn't change as time
goes on. It doesn't change as the
observer moves past it. It doesn't
change when the observer rotates. It's
not clustered. It's just uniformly
filling space, picks out no direction,
picks out no Lorentz frame,
and picks out no special time in the
sense that as the universe expands, it
doesn't change.
That's Energy of that type is called
vacuum energy.
If it exists at all, and it does seem to
exist.
What do we care? Why should we care if
the universe were filled with something
that we call vacuum energy? We do
experiments.
And the only thing we're interested in
this room, if we're doing experiments in
this room,
is differences of energy.
The zero point of energy really usually
doesn't matter for anything. The thing
which usually counts is differences of
energy.
What's the energy difference between an
excited atom and an unexcited atom?
What's the difference of having of the
energy with or without the atom?
The energy of an atom counts, but that's
because we can compare it to the energy
of a configuration without the atom.
But just empty space, who cares? We
could call we could just
put as much energy into empty space as
we as we like, as long as that energy
cannot turn into any other kind of
energy.
As long as it doesn't come into the
questions of differences of energy,
why should we care
if there's something called vacuum
energy in the room?
Well, the answer is what I said is we
don't care about the zero of energy
until
gravity becomes important.
Once gravity becomes important, what's
the source of the gravitational field?
The source of the gravitational field is
mass. Mass is energy.
Vacuum energy gravitates.
It has a gravitational effect. It has an
effect on space-time.
And it has an effect on space-time which
is different than if it weren't there.
So, let's talk about um
Well, the first question is, what's the
origin of vacuum energy?
And as I said, or somebody asked me
earlier,
vacuum energy
is It wasn't quite asked to me in these
terms, but vacuum energy is a feature of
quantum field theory.
Quantum field theory, quantum
electrodynamics, quantum
uh the standard model of particle
physics, all quantum field theories have
vacuum energy.
It's just the zero point energy, of the
oscillating fields, if you like.
There's a contribution to it from the
electromagnetic field. There's a
contribution to it from
electron-positron field. There's a
contribution to it from quark fields,
even if there are no quarks present. The
point is, you don't need to have
anything really present to have that
energy.
What is it due to? It's due to virtual
creation and annihilation. Virtual, you
remember, means that it happens so fast
that the little bit of energy that is
created and annihilated satisfies the
uncertainty principle.
If you create some particles out of
nothing, then they can only last for a
very short time because of the energy
time uncertainty principle. Let's leave
it at that.
Uh but the net result
is that there is energy density
called rho.
And it fills up space. It's everywhere.
It's Lorentz invariant. Doesn't matter
which uh how you're moving and so forth.
Vacuum energy. Let's call it rho vacuum.
Now what what does it do?
It has an effect on the right-hand side
of Einstein's equations. Let me remind
you what Einstein's equations are.
The details of them we don't need to
know.
I will write down as much of detail as
you need to know,
which is very little.
But let me just remind you what
Einstein's equations say. On the
left-hand side of right Einstein's
equations is a tensor
called G mu nu.
G stands for gravity,
I think.
Uh
it's a tensor
and it's made up out of
the metric components of space, the
metric of space. It's made up out of
the metric tensor. The metric tensor is
little G mu nu
of X.
Okay.
It's on the left-hand side. It's got to
do with curvature. It's got to do with
derivatives of the metric, uh
Christoffel symbols, all sorts of awful
stuff.
And by the time you write it down, it
takes up uh what G mu nu is, it takes up
a fair piece of space. Okay?
But it's got to do with Oh, I I said it
has to do with gravity. I'm not sure it
has to do with gravity.
I think maybe it has to do with
geometry, the G.
It's the geometric side of Einstein's
equations.
It says some property of the geometry of
space-time. This is space-time geometry,
not the geometry of space alone.
And on the right-hand side In other
words, it's the gravitational field.
Gravitational field, geometric field,
however you want to think about it. And
Einstein's field equations are that this
on the left-hand side
is equal to something
a numerical constant, but I'm not
interested in the numerical numerical
constant is 8 pi over 3, but not
important. On the right-hand side
is
the source of the gravitational field.
And the source of the gravitational
field is energy and momentum.
Energy
also known as mass and the motion of
masses, which is also known as momentum.
So on the right-hand side, there's
another tensor. It's called T mu nu.
I don't know why it's called T.
Uh but it's a thing which is made up out
of particles, out of ordinary fields,
not the gravitational field, the
electric field, the magnetic field.
And
if you know what this is, you know what
the what the ordinary energy density is,
the density of particles and so forth.
That's Einstein's field equation.
And
on the right-hand side is all the
various kinds of energy, both those
which dilute
particles, ordinary stuff, light, the
stuff which dilutes when the universe
expands, but also the stuff which
doesn't dilute,
the vacuum energy.
So
that's the reason we have to know about
vacuum energy, to know how geometry of
space-time behaves.
All right.
If there's only vacuum energy here,
I'll tell you what, I'm going to write
these equations I'm going to write them
out in full,
but for one very, very special case.
I told you that the left-hand side is
made up out of the metric tensor.
And let's take a very, very special case
for what geometry for what space-time
geometry is like. In some sense, it's
the simplest geometry that's not just
static
uh space just sitting there. I think we
actually wrote it out last time.
It was the expanding
uniformly expanding space that I told
you to think of as an infinite rubber
sheet where the infinite rubber sheet is
being stretched so that the coordinate
marks on it, we take a rubber sheet, we
mark it with coordinate marks X = 1, X =
2, X = 3, X = 4, and then we start to
stretch it.
Okay. The actual distance between
neighboring points increases with time,
and that's represented by writing a
metric. The metric
ds squared, that's the space-time
distance between pairs of points,
neighboring pairs of points.
Just as it would be in ordinary
Minkowski space, we start with a minus
This is pen This pen seems weak.
minus dt squared.
That's what we would have in ordinary
Minkowski space,
meaning flat space-time.
And then what we would have in Minkowski
space would be plus dx squared. Now dx
squared here stands for the dx squared
plus dy squared plus dz squared, which I
won't bother writing. It stands for the
ordinary
Euclidean
metric of ordinary space.
There would be some speeds of light in
here if I kept the speed of light
around, but I'm not.
All right.
But that's not the expanding space-time.
The expanding space-time you introduce
one more thing,
a thing called a scale factor, A of T.
A of T is a
function of time, is not a function of
space,
and it tells you Oops, I'm sorry. This
should be A squared of T.
A squared of T.
What it says is that if you take two
points,
let's say X = 0
and X = 1.
What's the distance between them?
Well, it's one unit. No, it's not one
unit because X doesn't actually measure
physical distance.
It's this which measures physical
distance. The actual distance between
them at any instant of time is A.
And as A changes with time, the distance
between these marked points
on the rubber sheet world,
the rubber sheet world, X = 0, X = 1,
the marked points separate, so A grows
with time.
It doesn't matter if they're separated
by one unit, two units. If we want to
separate them by um let's say this is X
= uh 7,
X = uh 13,
then the distance between them is
delta X. That's 13 minus 7, which is 4.
6. Thank you.
13 minus 7 times A.
A of T.
4.
13 minus 7 is A?
Is it 4? No, 13 minus 7 is 6. Thank you.
Right. Okay, that's the meaning of uh of
this metric.
They don't have to be on the X axis,
they can be off the X axis, but you get
the idea.
Okay.
This is a non-trivial geometry. It has
space-time curvature
unless A is constant.
It has And if A is constant, then it's
just flat space, good old flat space. If
A is varying with time, doing things,
maybe just expanding, that's enough to
make the space-time not flat.
The space may be flat, but space-time is
a different story. So space-time uh
expanding space-time is a new kind of
geometry that uh that's uh good.
Okay. Now, let's write down Einstein's
equations. What do Einstein's equations
have to do with?
They have to do with how A varies with
time.
A is the only thing in this geometry
that's not known. It's the only uh
degree of freedom for this kind of
geometry. For geometry of this type, all
of the geometry is coded in the
properties of A of T, which means A is a
function of time. So Einstein's field
equations must be simply equations for
how A varies with time, and they are.
And here's what they say.
They say that dA by dt
squared
is equal. I'm going to put in all the
factors now.
Uh
pi over 3
times Newton's constant
times the energy density
of matter.
The assumption here is that the energy
density of matter is completely uniform
in space.
You could have such a thing if space was
filled up with a uniform radiation bath
all at the same temperature. You could
have such a thing if if the universe was
filled up with atoms at a uniform
density.
So, we don't have to write row as a
function of X because row is not a
function of X.
But of course we do have to write row as
a function of time.
So, row is some function of time, but
what is row as a function of time? This
if we Oh, I'm sorry. There's a 1 over a
squared here. Whoops. 1 over a squared.
It's a dot over a squared.
Do you remember from last time what a
dot over a is?
It's the Hubble constant.
But let's leave it there. a dot over a
squared. That's it.
Okay. Now this equation also has another
significance in in general relativity,
it's one which confuses people. I get
zillions of emails. I get so many emails
about this particular point that I have
got can't keep up with them and I don't
even try anymore.
This equation is also an equation for
energy conservation. It expresses energy
conservation in general relativity.
Okay.
The right hand side is all of the energy
of ordinary stuff.
But it does not include the energy of
the gravitational field.
The gravitational field because it's
varying with time
a of t
also has energy.
And that energy is a kind of kinetic
energy. It's a kinetic energy of motion
or a kinetic energy of the time
dependence of the of the of the metric
of space time.
What is that
that energy? That energy is simply
the energy of
the varying gravitational It's called
the varying
um
scale factor. Energy of a varying scale
factor. A is called the scale factor.
One odd thing about it is that it's
negative in general relativity.
minus a dot over a
squared. There's probably a factor of 3
over 8 pi G.
3 over 8 pi G, I think.
It's not the It's not the number that's
important.
It's important that the formal structure
and the mathematical structure of
general relativity
gravity has energy
and some piece of the gravitational
energy is negative
and it corresponds to a negative kind of
kinetic energy of the gravitational
field.
So, what this equation can be written as
it can be written as minus this
plus this is equal to zero.
minus this plus this is equal to zero.
Well, zero is conserved. Zero doesn't
change with time. Zero is zero. It
doesn't change with time.
So, among other things, among the many
things that this says
is it says that energy doesn't change
with time. It also says the total energy
of the world is zero.
But it includes this piece coming from
expanding
space time which you're not used to
counting.
When we count the energy of this room,
we don't normally think about the fact
that the universe is expanding.
We just ignore it and we say the energy
in the room is positive.
Okay.
Uh
good.
Let's put it back the way that it was.
This equals this.
Uh let's go a little further now. Let's
ask what row of t is like. What the time
dependence of the energy density in the
world is like. So, let's come back
to this box.
It's not a real box. I've taken a region
of space and just drawn a mathematical
box.
The mathematical box has
a side delta x equals 1 on each side.
Okay.
How much energy is in it? Well, it's the
number of particles inside it.
Number of particles inside it which is
not going to change. As the box expands,
the particles move with it.
So that if this room if this room was
part of the expanding universe and you
were a bunch of protons
you would
expand you you the protons wouldn't
expand, but the distance between them
would expand so as to keep the proton
density uniform.
All right. So, there's n protons in
there. Each one has mass m. That's how
much total mass is in there. And what's
the volume of space? The volume of space
is
delta x times delta x times delta x.
That's 1, but
times a cubed. Why a cubed? Because the
actual length here
is
delta x
times a.
So, the side of the box here I've chosen
a box whose side
at any given time is a of t.
And so to find the density, I have to
divide it by a of t
cubed.
The only important thing here
is that at any time if I know the energy
This is the energy density. If I know
the energy at any given time
then I know it at all times. Not because
it stays the same, but because it always
scales like 1 over a of t cubed.
So, we can say that row of t then is
some number. We can call it row zero.
Row at some particular instant of time
divided by a of t cubed. So, now we can
come back to this formula over here.
And we can say, "Aha. I now have an
equation for a."
It's Einstein's equation for an
expanding universe and what goes over
here is some constant row naught
over a cubed.
One can solve this equation. Maybe we
should solve it.
Maybe we should solve it. It's not a
difficult equation.
It's much easier to solve if we take all
the constants 8 pi G over 3 times row
naught
and absorb them into a another constant.
Let's just call that other constant
Let's just call it row naught
and thereby erase this.
Good.
Okay. How do we solve this equation
here? Let's write out what it is. I bet
you can solve it.
I'll have you solve it. But first I'll
manipulate it a little bit.
This is a dot over This is the a d t
squared.
There's an a squared in the denominator,
but I'm going to multiply through and
put it on the other side. So, we
multiply by a squared and we get row
naught
divided by a. Is that right?
Right.
And now I take the square root of both
sides. Well, row naught
divided by a. I take the square root of
both sides.
square root of row naught
a to the 1/2
multiply
so that it reads a to the 1/2
times d a
equals square root of row naught times d
t.
a to the 1/2 on the side times d a
or just we could write it this way.
Can you
Can you solve that?
Yep. Say it again.
Right. You
What we're doing is integrating both
sides of this equation. What Michael
suggested
is to integrate both sides of this
equation.
On the right hand side we get square
root of row naught times time. The
integral of d t is just t.
And this one is what? 3/2
uh a to the 1/2 So, let's integrate it.
That's um
3/2.
No. 2/3.
2/3
a to the 3/2.
Is that correct?
And now we know a is a function of time.
Forgetting all the numerical constants 2
3 row naught what it says is that a
grows like t to the 2/3 power.
The scale factor grows like t to the 2/3
power because the energy density has a
particular behavior.
That's cosmology. That's standard
uh absolutely standard cosmological
expansion.
A growing like t to the 2/3.
Let's just draw it.
A
Let's first draw A growing like T.
There's A growing like T.
A
T
T to the 2/3 is smaller Well, it grows
less rapidly
than T itself. This is This large T is
smaller
and it looks like this.
Not quite a parabola
but it looks like that.
It slows down.
A uniform line like this would be an A
which grows linearly with time. It would
be like a coordinate of a particle
moving off with linear motion.
That's not what happens.
What happens is it turns over and it
appears to go slower and slower.
The universe decelerates
in this kind of cosmology. This is a
decelerating cosmology.
What is it that causes the universe to
decelerate?
Gravity is pulling everything.
Yeah.
Yes.
Another way to think about it is stuff
started out moving away from
each other and gravity just grabbed the
whole of it and slowed it down.
And
eventually it'll get slower and slower.
Okay, now let's ask what happens
if we have a different kind of energy on
the right-hand side.
We could put in if we want
Just for fun, I'm not going to do it
tonight. We could put in
radiation energy. Energy solely due to
radiation as if there were no particles,
only photons in the universe.
That would correspond You can work it
out yourself. That would correspond to
putting A to the fourth here.
I won't We don't have to go into that
now. It's just a fact. You can solve the
equations and find out how the universe
would expand if it were radiation
dominated.
The particular version that I gave you
is particle dominated.
It's usually called matter dominated.
Matter as opposed to radiation where the
energy
density decreases like 1 over A cubed.
Okay, but what happens now if there is
vacuum energy? If there really is vacuum
energy
vacuum energy has the property that it
never changes under any circumstances,
the density itself.
The density itself does not change under
any circumstances.
Uh we need to give it a name.
Let's
We'll put back for the moment we'll put
back the 8 pi's, G's, and so forth.
Theory tells us that it doesn't change.
Quantum field theory tells us it doesn't
change. It tells us that it's a sort of
universal constant
uh that can be calculated. Now, does
that mean that the universe that we know
with certainty that the universe is
filled up
with a kind of energy which doesn't
dilute as the universe expands?
Theory doesn't tell us that. What tells
us that is experiment and we'll talk
about the experiment in a minute. We'll
talk about all the observation in a
minute.
Theory tells us only what to put on the
right-hand side for various different
hypotheses about what the energy density
is. If the energy density is vacuum
energy in the sense of quantum field
theory, then it really is just constant.
Okay.
So, that means what goes on in the
right-hand side here does not vary with
A, does not vary as the universe
expands.
And let's just call it row vacuum. Let's
call it the vacuum energy density.
Row vacuum
is 8 pi G over 3
Sorry. A dot over A squared is 8 pi G
over 3 times this constant value of uh
of the energy density.
Now, first of all
if this is correct then one thing it
says is that the Hubble constant
A dot over A is the Hubble constant.
This is also H squared.
It tells us that H squared or H also 8
pi G over 3
times the vacuum energy that this
doesn't change with time.
Remember what the Hubble constant is.
The Hubble constant is the relationship
between distance and velocity.
Velocity is Hubble constant times
distance.
So, it says for all time in this kind of
world in this kind of world for all time
the relationship between velocity and
distance
is unchanged and always the same
numerical value.
That incidentally would not be true in
the uh in the other solution we wrote
down.
Uh normally for other kinds of cosmology
the Hubble constant decreases with time.
Here it just stays constant.
Right? An implication
is that the distance out to which you
have to go
in order to get to the speed of light
where stuff is moving away from you with
the speed of light that distance is
always the same.
It's given by C equals H times D or
equivalently C over H is equal to D. C
is a constant. H is a constant. The
distance out to the place where things
are receding with the speed of light
from us is fixed. Doesn't change with
time.
So, that's one implication of what this
means
to say that there's a constant value
here.
But let's see now if we can
if we can now solve
Einstein's equations for an expanding
universe.
Under the assumption that the only
energy density now
the only energy density is vacuum energy
density.
All right.
So, what do we have?
We have
A dot over A
squared
is equal to 8 pi G over 3
times row, but that's just the number H
squared. Let's just call it H squared.
Now, I'm using H now not to mean
definition. This is not definition now.
Previously
A dot over A was the definition of the
Hubble constant. Now, it's the numerical
value
of
8 pi G over 3 times row V. It's a
number.
It's a number
that
we don't know how to calculate it. We
don't know the theory of it.
But it's a number. H squared is now a
number.
Everybody understand the difference
between saying H squared is A dot over A
as a definition and H squared is A dot
over A square as a uh
as a
numerical relationship? Here H is not
defined this way. It just is a number.
It's It's measured.
It is measured. It is measured. It's a
measured number and it's not expected to
and there's evidence that it is not
changing with time.
Right? So, it's a number.
How do we solve this equation? Well,
first of all we take its square root.
A dot
We multiply it by A and it reads A dot
is equal to H times A.
I think some fraction of you can solve
this equation.
Nobody can solve it?
Right.
A dot A
is equal to E to the HT.
This is the equation that tells us that
the growth rate of A is proportional to
A itself.
Exponential growth with time.
A thing which changes by an amount
proportional to its own value
exponentially grows.
And the growth factor, the time factor,
the time constant for this is H. E to
the HT
is the way this universe is growing.
Okay.
Exponentially. You can put a constant in
front of it.
The constant doesn't matter much.
So, this is an exponentially growing
universe.
That's the result of vacuum energy.
Vacuum energy really is important and
the way to detect it Well, I'll give you
two ways to detect it. One is
astronomical. Measure the Hubble
constant and measure the Hubble constant
over a period of time
and see whether it's staying constant.
Or you can measure the scale factor A
over a period of time and see whether
it's expanding exponentially.
Either way. There's another way that you
can measure it in the laboratory.
There's no way you're actually going to
do this.
But if you had The laboratory now means
way out in outer space. Take two objects
which are very light and therefore
their gravitational between them is not
very important.
Start them out at rest.
And if they're light enough so that
gravity between them is unimportant,
they will just expand with the
expansion.
And you can measure the rate at which
the distance between them expands with
time.
Make sure there's nothing else present.
Complete vacuum. So, the only
possibility is vacuum energy distorting
space. And you would discover that these
begin to accelerate and begin to expand,
separate from each other exponentially.
So, that's how you would build a vacuum
energy detector.
Now, of course, the effect in the real
world is so minuscule that you couldn't
even begin to hope to detect this
uh in the laboratory, but you can detect
it
uh cosmologically.
How do you detect it cosmologically?
A number of ways, but uh
but
I'm sorry.
You say, "Well, we have to we have to
check that H is constant with time.
That's going to take a long, long time."
But, no, not really. We When we look out
at the distant universe, we see it at
different times.
And we can actually measure the Hubble
constant at different times by looking
at it at different length scales.
Or we can look what's comes to the same
thing is we can measure the expansion
rate, or we can measure how A varies
with time.
All right, so I'll tell you now how it
varies with time.
Oh, wait. Uh let's uh let's point
something else out.
The real world doesn't just have an H
squared.
It also has some other energy density.
Let's add in the other energy density.
It was called rho naught divided by A
cubed, for example.
When A is small, when the universe is
small, when the scale factor is small,
this term is going to be much bigger
than this. Why is that? Because A is in
the denominator, that's why. So, early
on
in the real world, this is not very
important,
and this may be very important when A is
small. In that case, we worked it out a
few minutes ago, and we found out that A
goes like t to the 2/3.
It goes like this.
But now, as A grows,
eventually
this term
will get small, whereas this one is not
getting small.
This one's not diluting, this one is
diluting.
So, eventually the diluting term gets
smaller than the non-diluting term.
And then, after that, you can basically
forget it.
Once this term gets smaller than this
term, you can forget it.
And how does A behave? A behaves like e
to the HT.
So, what you expect in a world that has
both kinds of energy is that early on
the scale factor
or the radius of the universe, or the
the radius the the distance between
distant galaxies
grows this way.
But then, at some time
when the vacuum energy becomes more
important than the other forms of
energy, it takes off
exponentially.
Exponentially, something like that.
When you solve that differential
equation, you end up with a the C in
front of the With the what? With the
integration constant in front of the
uh e to the HT. Yeah, there's a there's
an integration constant here.
Uh
how do you know that that integration
constant isn't really small or
Well, you measure it.
You measure it. You measure it.
You measure it. And
at here's t,
here's A.
And of course, when you measure A, you
don't just measure A now, as I said. You
measure A by looking out deeper and
deeper into distant galaxies, you can
measure the distance between different
distant galaxies at earlier times.
And so, at one time,
you can measure this whole curve up to
some point. You can't measure what it's
going to be in the future,
but you can measure what it was in the
past. So, if this is now,
we get to measure all of this curve, and
it looks something like that. It looks
something like that, approximately
something like this.
With this branch of it here being fit
rather accurately to uh
uh to an exponential. I won't I won't
try to tell you how accurately.
Uh it's about a 5%
the the proper figure of merit
is about a 5%
uh
It's not a deviation, it's
exponential plus or minus 5%.
Okay, so that looks to most um
cosmologists, that looks fairly
convincing that we live in a world with
vacuum energy.
Certainly, we don't know anything else
that would have much chance of doing
precisely this.
And uh it's a um
It's
It's not a fact in the same sense that
we know that uh that the electron exists
or that the fine structure constant is 1
over 137. blah blah blah blah,
but uh by now, it's pretty much
considered a fact of cosmology
that we live in a world with vacuum
energy, and that we live in an
exponentially expanding world.
That's uh pretty remarkable in a way.
Any questions?
I have a quick question. I I've In some
uh books I've seen, if you take a
a our position right now and draw a a
the slope
that down.
Now, we can if if that slope intersects
to
uh to the left of the origin, you can
see back to the Big Bang. And as as it
exponentially goes up, there'll be a
time where you
can't see past the Big Bang. Is that
Um In other words, we'll expand away so
far that the
uh
I don't quite understand that that point
isn't important. Well,
um
I'm not sure it's an issue of expanding
back to uh tracing back to the Big Bang.
Or or to the or to the begin the cosmic
background radiation uh emission and
stuff.
in in the sense that the Hubble distance
is related to the age of the universe.
In sense that the Hubble Yeah.
Um
Right, the Hubble
Right, in this exponentially increasing
world here, the Hubble scale is not
related to the age of the universe.
It's just a constant, right? But but at
some point, you
uh
Oh, I I I don't know.
The There's a horizon. There's a
horizon. We're going to talk about
horizons. We're going to talk about
event horizons. There's a lot of
different kinds of horizons on the
market.
But the only ones which are deep and
fundamental
interest are event horizons.
So, we're going to talk about event
horizons. So, let's uh let's now just
put in our back pocket this piece of
knowledge that the world is
exponentially expanding,
that
we can summarize everything that was on
the blackboard.
Oh, there is an interesting fact. If the
world continues to exponentially expand
like this,
then all of the dilutable matter, the
kind the energy that dilutes with
expansion, is just going to get more and
more and more diluted.
Right?
So, in some number of um
billions of years,
the material in the universe will
stretch out so much that it will become
of negligible density. And the only
energy left over will be the vacuum
energy. It'll become a very dull world,
uh
but so be it.
Does that mean that um
the galaxies which aren't expanding
today because gravity holds them
together?
No, they they won't expand. They won't
expand.
Uh what will happen is the few galaxies
which are close enough to us
which and which happen just by accident,
more or less, to be falling toward us.
There's one or two galaxies which are
actually falling toward us.
Uh that's a sort
When we say that everything uniformly
expands, of course, it uniformly expands
plus or minus little bits of
fluctuation.
It happens that there's a little bit of
fluctuation in our neighborhood which
happened to cause the Andromeda galaxy
to be somewhat moving toward us.
So,
us and the Andromeda are not going to
separate from each other, but uh but you
know, if you go out a few more galaxies,
they're certainly moving with the flow.
Anything which is moving with the flow
will eventually depart. It will just
grow and separate and separate and
separate.
And after a few hundred billion years,
all that will be left for us to see is
us, our galaxy, and that's it. We will
be living in a world
where
you'll be able to see out to enormously
large distances, but you won't see
anything.
Well, astronomers who are born at that
time and don't have a good record of
history will come to the amazing
conclusion that they are alone in the
universe.
Uh yeah.
Doesn't that say that you eventually
exceed the gravitational attraction
because
our galaxy is gravitationally bound to a
group? Yeah.
And if the group expands, then No, no,
no. If the group expands, then then
we're not gravitationally bound. Right.
So, when you said all of you can see is
our galaxy. And the Andromeda.
Which by that time probably will have
crashed into us and formed some sort of
single structure. But are each of the
clusters gravitationally bound to each
other also?
Currently. Yes, they are.
So,
Not No No
No, no. It depends on what you mean by a
cluster. If you look at the at
um a few galaxies out, not very many,
just a few
one or two more, they're moving away
from us.
Even though they form what's called a
cluster.
Well, they're gravitationally bound, but
they're attracted No, they're not
gravitationally bound. No, they're not
gravitationally bound. Gravitationally
bound means that they won't that the
that they that they won't separate.
So, the so the the measure of
gravitationally bound depends on this
expansion rate.
Yeah, but not very much. But not very
hardly at all. Hardly at all. For nearby
things,
if they're gravitationally bound can
just mean whether
just forget
forget this expansion and just ask
whether they're moving relative to each
other with less than or greater than the
escape velocity.
That That's what gravity All right.
Now, it happens as a more or less
accidental fact that the Andromeda
happens to be moving toward us.
A few galaxies out,
they're moving away from us and they
will continue to move away from us.
They're moving away from us with greater
than the escape velocity.
And they'll continue.
Yeah, um
If you take a galaxy, the is a constant,
never changes
Mhm. with time. Mhm. But the outward
force due to
the vacuum energy
is a function of time. It grows and It
grows with distance. It grows linearly
with distance.
It grows with distance. But not with
time.
No, not with time except in so far as
things separate with time.
Two objects
will separate with time. Their distance
will become larger and for that reason
the the repulsive force will increase.
But the total repulsive force does not
increase with Okay, you have a small
repulsive very small repulsive force
now.
And over a period of billions of years,
the repulsive force seems to be question
that it's sort of cumulative. There's
a bigger amount of repulsive force.
That's only because things get further
away from each other. But but a but a
but a galaxy won't get further away from
each other.
If the galaxy if two galaxies are at the
same distance at a later time as they
are now,
the component of the
little repulsion from the vacuum energy
will be the same.
Okay, what I was asking is that the the
net gravitational force is G minus the
expansion force.
And if the expansion if the if the force
the the tendency towards expanding
increases,
um
it wouldn't be net effect be that G very
gradually decreases?
And that
That doesn't make sense. No, what he's
saying is that the force is a function
of distance, not a function of
It's a function of distance, not a
function of time.
If you have two objects if you have two
objects
at distance R between them at any time,
doesn't matter what time, there are two
components to the force. One of them is
G * M1 M2
uh divided by uh by R squared. And then
there's another force on each of them or
there's another force
uh
which is um
proportional to
It has a G in it, but mainly it's
proportional to and repulsive. This is
minus meaning attractive. Plus a
repulsive force proportional to R
itself, to the distance between them.
if the change doesn't change
Coefficients don't change. What does
change is the distance between things.
Okay? So, as the distance grows, this
will become less important. This will
become more important.
But you can ask where does this become
important relative to this?
The answer is when the distance scales
are pretty cosmological.
You know, 5 billion light years or
something like that. The crossover The
coefficient of this piece is so small
that the crossover between the normal
gravitational attraction and the bit of
repulsion is on a billions of light
years scale.
Uh so,
that's why you can't measure it by
in a laboratory.
So, it's not just a function of the of
expanding space that is represented as a
repulsive force. It's actually
It is the It is the expanding space, but
you can you can fake it by a
by a force which is pushing everything
else apart from each other.
It's a slight fake, but but it sort of
works
the right way.
Yeah.
Um
Okay.
We've now
Now,
does that That kind I think satisfies my
my curiosity here that
in the early universe, these galaxies
were gravitationally bound.
And the expansion has now taken them to
where
the
vacuum
expansion, this other factor R. In the
early universe, they were not
gravitationally bound.
It's crossed over.
So, the gravitational attraction field
is
fallen below When they When they get far
enough apart,
then the repulsion becomes more
important than the attraction. Right.
So, in the early universe, they were
gravitationally bound.
Well, yeah, this was not important in
the early universe. Right.
That's another statement.
It's two state two different statements
to say that they're gravitationally
bound and that the important force was
the ordinary gravitational force.
If we shoot a rocket off the surface of
the Earth at 1 and 1/2 times the escape
velocity, it is not gravitationally
bound. But still the most important
force on it is the ordinary
gravitational force. These are two
different statements.
One statement, gravitationally bound,
means it's going to come back. The other
statement is
this may be more important than this in
the early universe, and it was, but it
doesn't mean that the that the galaxies
were gravitationally bound. They were
still moving apart from each other with
greater than the escape velocity.
Uh for the most part, I mean.
Uh
pretty much.
Galaxies were sort of shot out pretty
much greater than the escape velocity
between them.
Um
Or
at roughly at very close to the escape
velocity. Very, very close to the escape
velocity. Extremely close to the escape
velocity. And then
they either turn around and fall back in
or they they accelerate away from each
other depending on whether there's this
kind of new energy.
Okay, um
Let's take a little break. And when we
come back, I will tell you more about
the geometry of
this kind of space and why it has
horizons. What it means for it to have
horizons.
So, now that we know
that in a couple of hundred billion
years,
the universe is going to be described
And it's all it's it's getting that way
pretty quickly, actually. On the scale
of tens of billions of years, we're
getting there pretty fast. Uh we're
getting to a
condition where the geometry of
space-time is described
by
a metric.
And the metric is E to the 2 HT. That's
A squared
* DX squared.
And again, DX squared stands for DX
squared + DY squared + DZ squared and
this is the scale factor.
Um
This space-time, it's a space-time. It
has a geometric property.
It has a name. Anybody know what the
name is?
De Sitter space. De Sitter space. D E
It's De Sitter space.
Should be called De Sitter space-time,
obviously, but it's called De Sitter
space.
And
I'd like to examine its properties a
little bit.
Not because
not because um
uh
we're going to be sending rocket ships
out there to explore it. That's going to
take a while. But just for the
intellectual value of understanding the
space-time that we live in.
That's pretty weird. It's pretty weird.
It Of course, it looks weird, but it's
weirder than it looks.
Um It's weird in that it has horizons.
Before we get into horizons of De Sitter
space,
let's just talk for a moment about what
horizons are in general.
And
I'll give as the illustration the
horizon of a black hole.
Remember we worked out what a black hole
formation, a black hole which is created
by an infalling
collection of material, what it looks
like. And we drew a Penrose diagram.
Penrose diagram looked like that. Before
we do that, let's We're going to We're
going to use Penrose diagrams.
So, because it's helpful.
But, let's first draw the Penrose
diagram of ordinary flat space.
There's ordinary flat space. There's
points far away at spatial infinity.
Here's time infinity. Light rays come in
from here and they go out from here and
all that sort of stuff. And that's just
empty space.
Okay?
A black hole space-time looks like this.
Oh, one other point.
Imagine
an object, a massive object, not a
photon, a massive object
in this space. How does a massive object
move through space-time?
Well,
all massive objects wind up at the same
place.
They won't Massless objects, photons, go
out the sides here,
moving with the speed of light. Massive
objects,
they all go to this point up here.
Now, that's not really a point.
It's not really a point. It's a whole
big space-time that's been smooshed into
a onto the diagram to look small.
Well, obviously, if we wanted to take
all of space-time and squeeze it onto
the blackboard, we're going to have to
distort it pretty badly.
And it's very distorted up here in that
there's an infinite amount of space and
time up in this corner. Likewise here,
likewise here. In fact, on all of the
edges.
And all of
the massive objects eventually wind up
at this corner. That's not to say that
they get close together.
It's just to say that uh this is a very
big place up here.
Okay.
Now, let's think of the massive objects
in the black hole space.
In the black hole space, you can have
one of two things happening.
The massive object can fall into the
horizon
and hit the singularity.
Let's avoid that.
Let's avoid that. Let's talk about the
objects which don't fall into the
singularity.
Where do they go?
They go to here. They all do.
Again, that doesn't mean that they
literally get close together. It just
means there's a lot of space-time out
there.
Okay.
All of these people wind up Let's draw
the horizon. The horizon's over here.
Okay, now let's ask what these people
here can see as they look back into the
past.
They can see only those things which are
inside their backward light cone.
Backward light cone means take all light
rays which can get to this point over
here.
All the light rays
come in from here and take that region.
That's the region that he over here can
be aware of.
When he looks back, he can only see the
things inside his light cone.
Same for this guy over here.
Same for this observer.
They can see the things in their
backward light cone.
Now, how much can they see given
arbitrary amounts of time?
Given arbitrary amounts of time, they
can look back from later and later
times.
And eventually, they can see
all of this blue region here.
What they cannot see is what's in here.
A horizon is by definition the place
which separates the region that these
observers can see from where they can't
see. Given enough time,
you draw the backward light cone of a
very future point along that observer's
trajectory,
and that is the region he can see.
Everything on the other side is behind
the horizon, and the horizon is the
separation between them.
Here, there's no horizon.
An observer way up here gets back,
looks back, and sees everything.
Sees the entire space-time. No horizon.
Here, there's a horizon.
So, I just remind you of that to
tell you what a horizon is.
We're now going to take this metric.
And we're going to do a little bit of
mathematics on it. It's not hard
mathematics. It's pretty easy
mathematics.
It's not particularly abstract,
but it uh helps us visualize the
space-time.
What we're going to do with it is we're
going When I'm not going to try to take
all of space and squeeze it onto the
blackboard. I'm going to leave space
infinite. But, what I'm going to take do
is take the time axis,
and I'm going to smoosh it.
I'm going to make a coordinate
transformation of time so that I can put
the entire time from minus infini- Well,
not from minus infinity. Minus infinity
will be deep down in the floor,
but plus infinity will be in some finite
place here. Because we're going to want
to We're going to want to
study
what this world is like at late times.
And I'd like to get the whole infinite
future
onto the blackboard.
Not the whole infinite future of space,
but the whole infinite future of time.
So, we're going to make a coordinate
transformation.
And we're going to do this in a way that
makes light rays move on 45° angles in
this space.
It's always good to do that. Always get
the light rays moving at 45° angles, and
it's easy to see what can communicate
with what.
All right, so here's the trick.
We're going to change coordinates. We're
going to introduce a new coordinate. I'm
going to call it capital T.
And it's a function
of the old T.
And it's going to have the property
Here's the property it's going to have.
It's going to be such that dT squared
What appears here is going to be equal
to
e to the 2 HT, exactly what appears
here,
times d capital T squared.
This is the definition of capital T.
It's a new time a new time coordinate,
and it's related to the old time
coordinate by a pretty simple equation.
We're going to solve it.
And then we're going to rewrite the
metric
with the new time in place of the old
time, and the metric will have a nice
appearance that will allow us to explore
it very nicely.
Okay, how do I solve for big T as a
function of little t?
The first thing I do is take the square
root of both sides of the equation.
dt
is equal to e to the ht d capital T.
And now divide
by e to the ht. What do I get on the
left-hand side if I divide by e to the
ht?
e to the minus ht, right? So, we'll put
an e to the minus ht here.
And now we have dt.
Well, all we have to do to find the
relationship between big T and little t
is to integrate.
The integral on the right-hand side just
gives us T.
What about the left-hand side? Anybody
can do that integral?
Dime for anybody 1 over h.
1 over h.
Minus sign?
e to the minus ht, right?
Okay.
Plus a
Plus a constant, but we can fix the
constant uh
by just shifting T here.
Right, there's a constant, but I can
shift the constant Suppose I put a
constant There's a constant. Now, I just
redefine T so that it's T plus C.
It doesn't make any difference, right?
Okay, now notice first of all, capital T
is negative.
Let's just think about what happens to
it. This 1 over h here, not so
important. Let's see what happens to it.
What is it like at very remote past
times? Let's say when little t here is
extremely negative.
What happens to e to the minus ht?
It becomes very big.
If T is negative, and we have e to the
minus, then it's This becomes e to a a
positive number,
a big positive number. This gets very
big, but there's a negative sign out
here.
So, that means the remote past,
where little t is very, very negative,
is also the remote past from the point
of view of big T.
When little t gets very, very negative,
so does big T.
All right?
So, in both variables,
the remote past is way down through the
floor in the basement and even deeper.
Okay.
What about the remote future?
What happens in the remote future to
capital T?
The remote future is when little t is
very, very big.
What happens to this when little t is
very big?
It goes to zero.
So, big T goes to zero in the remote
future. Now, we can draw the
the time axis to Let's draw the time
the big T axis.
The big T axis
goes into the very remote past
in the negative region.
Deep past.
But, where is the infinite future? The
infinite future is right at capital T
equals zero.
Capital T equals zero, that also is
little t equals infinity.
So, big T runs from minus infinity up to
zero.
That's one way of getting not the whole
geometry on the blackboard, but getting
the remote future
onto the blackboard. That was a goal.
Okay, let's Let's see if we can rewrite
the metric. Let's see if we can rewrite
the metric in terms of big T instead of
little t.
Right?
So, here we have Let's Here's little t
squared. What's the relation between
There's little dt here. Little dt
Here it is.
Little dt
is equal
to e
to the big HT
times big T, right?
Good?
I just multiplied by e to the HT
to get it over on this side over here.
And now we come to this metric over
here. We have minus dt squared.
So, this is equal then to minus
dt squared, but that's e to the 2 HT
the big T squared.
And then we have plus
e to the 2 HT
dx squared.
In other words, I've engineered it
so that the e to the 2 HT would come on
the outside.
It would be equal to e to the 2 HT
times
a common
Minkowski space metric.
This would be the metric of ordinary
flat space-time. Minus dt squared plus
dx squared plus dy squared plus dz
squared.
But, it has this factor in front of it.
How about this factor that's in front of
it? What can we do with it?
I want to re-express it in terms of
capital T. So, let's do that.
Let's first multiply by H.
E to the minus HT
equals H times big T. All I did was
multiply by by H.
And now let's square it.
If I square it, the minus sign goes away
and I get e to the minus 2 HT.
And this side I get H squared T squared.
And finally
I take one over it.
So, that e to the 2 HT
is equal to 1 over H squared
T squared.
Go through it. Check the arithmetic.
You'll find it works that way.
And now we can write this metric
just by substituting for e to the 2 HT 1
over H squared T squared.
So, let's put that there. In fact, let's
write it over here.
The S squared
is equal
to 1 over H squared T squared
times
minus dt squared
plus dx squared. Okay, now this is a
long story.
Nice simple result.
But, the main point of it, the main
point of it
is that we've written the metric as an
ordinary Minkowski space metric times a
function.
With the same function appearing
multiplying all of this.
How do light rays move in this geometry?
What's
What What's the rule for light ray?
The
ds is zero.
Right. Light rays move on paths
of
zero proper time.
Okay?
What does that say?
That says that you can forget this
factor altogether when you're thinking
about a light ray.
If you want to know how a light ray
moves, you don't need to know about this
factor.
All you need is this factor.
Right?
Everybody see that?
If you want to know how a light ray
moves, it moves exactly as it would
if this were just ordinary flat
space-time. How do light rays move in
flat space-time?
On straight lines tilted at a 45° axis
to the vertical.
Okay. So, we now know
in this geometry how light rays move.
Let's draw the geometry. Here it goes.
It starts out deep in the past. We can't
go down that deep into the basement.
But, it ends
This is space. Space now goes this way
and this way.
It ends at capital T equals zero.
How can it end at capital T equals zero?
Little t went on and on forever.
Well, it's just that
that the metric
when little t when big T gets small
the metric here blows up. It gets big.
So, that means there's a lot of time in
here.
The metrical distance between
neighboring points gets very large
when T goes to zero.
So, it's highly distorted. I mean, it's
a highly distorted geometry. The one
advantage of it is that light rays move
on 45° axes.
So, we now know how light rays move.
They move like that.
If they're moving out of the blackboard,
they also move on 45°, but I'm not going
to try to draw it.
I can't draw it.
All right. Good.
Now, let's ask what an observer can see.
Imagine an observer in this world.
Make him blue.
Here she is.
She's standing still in her own
reference frame.
Time is going on. More and more and more
time is unfolding.
And eventually
she gets up to the top. Now, how long
does that take according to her watch?
Forever. Right? Takes forever for her
for that to happen.
Uh
But, on this diagram, on this formal
mathematical abstract description of de
Sitter space
the terminal point is over there. That's
the end of her existence.
Doesn't bother her at all because her
clock has gone off to infinity.
Let's ask what she can see.
What she can see as she looks back.
All right, let's draw that in red.
Here she is right over here. That's
Alice. And Alice looks back
and sees everything that she can see
within her light cone.
Remember, the whole purpose of this
coordinate transformation was to make it
easy to follow light rays. 45°.
If we want more dimensions, we'll have
to
extend this out to make a cone out of
it.
But, you can see all of main features
from here. She can see everything behind
her here.
But, if she waits a little while, she
sees more.
And if she waits a little longer, she
But, no matter how long she waits
the most that she can ever see
is this.
What about things out here?
Nothing.
If there's somebody out here, she can
never know about it in principle.
She has a horizon.
The red line out here is her event
horizon. It is her private event
horizon. Other people have different
event horizons.
But, this is her private event horizon.
She cannot see anything out beyond it.
In principle As a matter of real
principle
she cannot at least by classical
relativistic reasoning, by classical
light reasoning and so forth she cannot
see anything All kinds of things could
be going on there.
Uh
Her friend Bob might have originated
over here and she might have been able
to see Bob in the past.
From here she could even see Bob is
moving. There's Bob.
Alice
Bob.
In the past Alice was able to send
messages to Bob. Bob was able to send
messages to Alice, and now Bob passes
Alice's horizon.
From there on in, Bob cannot send a
message to Alice.
Bob may be able to see Alice, but Alice
cannot see Bob. Okay?
Uh
Here's Bob.
So, from this point on, Bob has passed
out of her horizon. He's gone.
That's what's going to happen
unless of course if she's holding hands.
What What does it look like if she's
holding hands with Bob and she doesn't
want to let him go?
Yeah.
Then
it looks like this. Now, does this mean
they really get closer and closer
together?
No, it doesn't. It doesn't because the
metric is getting bigger and bigger out
here.
So, the actual metrical distance between
them, actual proper distance between
them can stay constant. And if it does
stay constant, they would
appear to join up here, but they're not
really getting any closer together. So,
if they're bound together, if they're
holding hands, this is what it looks
like, and they can continuously forever
and ever send messages back and forth.
Uh no uh
no limits.
But, if Bob lets go of Alice and goes
with the flow, if he's Let's go implies
among other things that he gets far
enough away that the gravitational pull
between them doesn't hold them together.
If he lets go
and passes outside her horizon, they
simply fall out of causal contact.
That's the expression for it. They've
fallen out of causal contact. In this
particular instance, Bob can send a
message Oh, sorry. Can receive a message
from Alice, but he can never send a
message to Alice.
Uh
Alice up here
cannot send a message to Bob either
because Bob also has his own private
event horizon.
Let's make Bob's event horizon in green.
Here's Bob's event horizon.
Bob cannot see anything outside of his
event horizon.
So, he can see Alice early on,
but he can't see Alice after she passes
out of her horizon. Yeah. So, he won't
be actually able to see Alice What's
that? at his time. Say it again. Bob
won't be able to see Alice at in his
time.
That's right. Bob Well, you can never
see anything at the same time, period.
Right. You can never see your The only
thing you can ever see is those things
which are back inside your past light
cone.
Okay? So, you never can see anybody at
the same time.
But, once Bob has passed through here,
Alice can never see him.
If this really was flat space, if it
really wasn't this peculiar de Sitter
space with this factor here which
terminates it, then Alice could keep
going and look back at Bob.
But, Alice comes to the end of her world
line over here and simply cannot look
back.
So, this is the character of
de Sitter space. It has horizons.
In fact, every single observer
has his own private event horizon.
In this case, Alice and Bob are
constitute one observer.
And uh
maybe we'll talk a little bit more about
these event horizons next next time.
Um I'm getting a little tired, so I
think I'll quit soon.
But, we apparently live in such a world.
And in such a world, it's not Alice and
Bob, but it's galaxies. Lots of
galaxies.
Here we are now.
We can see about 10 to the 22 galaxies
around us.
As time goes on, they will pass through
the horizon and pass out
out of Let's Let's say we're Alice.
They will pass out of Alice's horizon,
and Alice will not be able to see them
anymore. They will be gone.
Uh So, as I said, Alice will be alone in
the world for all practical purposes.
Um
Excuse me. Is there Is there a theory
that in in
the far distance, we would not be able
to see any
any galaxies at all? That's right.
That's right. They will have uh
Galaxy Alice
and Bob will
They're like gravitationally
Okay. That's it.
You might You might Okay. Let Let's
Let's ask whether Alice at a very very
late time here
uh can see Bob back here.
And a very In a sense, no. It looks like
he can, but in the sense, no, and I'll
explain why.
Um
This is Alice, yeah. Alice's time steps
look like this.
Many many time steps here. Now, imagine
that Bob sends her a signal,
and that signal
is going to come up to here.
Uh Alice is going to look back and look
for Bob back here. Well, you say she can
see him.
But, in fact, because her time clocks
are so bunched up over here, it means
the radiation that she sees from Bob is
incredibly red shifted.
That
how many beats of Bob's uh clock
get squeezed into Alice's
time scale here. One beat of her clock
gets stretched out over an enormous time
scale from Alice's world. So, when Alice
looks back and sees Bob from way way up
here, he's enormously red shifted. You
can't see very very red shifted things.
His uh his wavelength uh wavelength of
his light and the energy of his light
will be so stretched out. So, in fact,
really Alice has no chance of really
seeing Bob over here.
He's just been red shifted to hell and
uh
and It's like a black hole, right?
What's that? Like on the horizon. It's
very similar That's right. It's exactly
the same as in the horizon of a black
hole. So, in that sense, at very very
late time, Alice will not be able to see
any of the galaxies except in this
exceedingly red shifted sense, which is
useless. She can't detect such low
energy radiation. And she will just find
herself alone, and so will Bob.
All other galaxies having passed out of
their horizon. Is it the same with the
black hole where it takes forever to
reach the horizon?
Yeah, yeah, but they Okay.
It is It is the same. It is the same.
Um Well, it is the same. Alice looks
back.
Has Bob crossed her Where is Bob? Here's
Bob over here.
Has Bob crossed the horizon? No. Alice
looks back. Has Bob crossed the horizon?
No. Alice looks back. Has Bob crossed
the horizon? No.
She never sees him cross the horizon.
But, do objects uh falling into black
hole um
become infinitely red shifted as well?
Yes. Yes, it's exactly the same thing.
It's exactly the same thing.
Okay.
Here's the black hole.
Here's who stays outside. Let's put
Alice outside.
Yeah, let's put Alice outside.
Let's keep the color coding.
Blue. Blue for Alice.
Alice is red. Bob is green. No, here's
Alice. Alice is blue. Bob is green.
Yeah.
I don't know. Here's
Here Here's Alice.
I I usually send Alice into the black
hole, but this time Alice gets to stay
outside. And here's her clock. Her clock
is going faster and faster and faster
and faster and faster.
So, it's not going faster and faster,
but on this diagram, all her time
intervals are bunched up, same as they
are over here.
And
Bob, who is now green,
is falling through the horizon.
Alice looks back.
Does she ever get to see
Bob fall through? No.
Bob's signals, his light waves or his
waves of his hand that he sends out,
appear to get slower and slower to her
because they're drawn out over longer
and longer time scales, which is another
way of saying
Alice becomes infinitely red shifted.
The light from Alice becomes infinitely
red shifted from Bob's perspective. So,
it's exactly the same thing. Yeah. So,
in Alice's real time, right? She in her
proper time, she's slowing down. I mean
She what? She's going at her proper
time.
She just But, on the scale, it's like
it's getting compressed, right? Well, on
the scale
not on her scale Well,
she's just ticking along happily.
No, that's Bob. That's Bob. Oh, that's
No, that's That's Bob. You're right.
That's Bob, yes.
That's Bob, yes. Good.
So, Alice's scale time, right?
Yeah. Her proper time is still her
proper time, right?
So, she looks back and she sees Bob
slowing down. Yeah. Right? But, then
But, she not only sees him slowing down,
she sees his atoms slowing down. She
sees the radiation that's coming
out She Who is it?
Yeah, she sees not only Bob slowing
down, but she sees the atoms slowing
down. She sees the emission of photons
getting slower and slower, the photons
getting longer and longer wavelength,
smaller and smaller frequency,
and eventually his photons become so
monumentally long wavelength
that they can't be seen at all.
The energy of them gets gets diminished
to negligible. Yeah. How would you
measure the temperature of the
surface right above the horizon?
Well, to do that, she has to send down a
thermometer and make sure the
thermometer doesn't fall into the black
hole.
So, to keep it from falling through the
black hole, she'd send down a
thermometer,
measure the temperature, pull it back
up, and see what it recorded.
But, that's not what she's doing with
Bob. Bob is
And the same incidentally, same thing
here.
If
if Alice
All right, so here would be the
experiment. Alice has a very long rope,
a long cable. On the end of the cable is
a thermometer. She throws it out hard
enough that it's beyond the escape
velocity from from our local cluster
galaxies,
and waits a long time for it to migrate
out toward the horizon, her horizon.
But, she doesn't let it go through the
horizon. She then pulls it back in.
And after she's pulled it back in, she
sees what the what the temperature that
it recorded was. She will also see a
high temperature, but we'll come to
that. Horizons are always
hot in the sense,
but we'll come to that. This is this is
so far the classical description of de
Sitter space, full of horizons. There's
horizons everywhere, no matter where
Alice is,
there's somebody
she's passing through somebody's
horizon.
So, wherever you are, you're passing
through somebody's horizon. Say goodbye,
because you won't see them again.
Yes. I'm trying to understand what it
looks like in the untransformed
with the in the little T. Yeah. And
they're at the same distance. I'll I'm
going to leave it I'll leave that for
you for to do an exercise. It's an
exercise to see what it looks like. Uh
No, no, it's a good exercise. Just
undo undo what I did, and it's Just say
that my assumption is they're not moving
apart. There's the axis is not expanding
here,
or is
No, no, no, no, no. The whole metric is
blowing up, including the X parts of it.
So, the distance between points, if you
keep the points at fixed coordinate
separation, here Bob and Alice are at
fixed X's,
the distance between them is getting
bigger and bigger. Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
Good.
Yeah. It goes to e to the infinity
there.
That's right. The distance between them
blows up when they get up to uh
Right. That's another fact of de Sitter
space.
Now,
something you can work out is you can
compare
the distances between these two points
with the distance between these two
points, with the distance between these
two points, between the distance between
the
comparing how far apart are these two,
how far apart are these two, how far
apart are these two, how far apart are
these two.
What do you think the answer is?
Hm?
Are they growing, shrinking?
No, it's staying the same. Staying the
same. Yeah.
If you draw a horizontal line, you can
work it out. Here's the metric.
Draw a horizontal line here and ask for
the distance, let's say, from the center
to the horizon over here.
And compare it with the distance from
the center to the horizon over here.
Compare it with the distance from the
center to the horizon over here. You'll
find they're all the same.
The coordinate distance is shrinking,
but the metric is increasing, and the
distance to the horizon is always the
same.
That is connected with the fact that the
Hubble constant is constant, and so the
distance to where the speed of light is
where the where the uh
things are moving away with the speed of
light is constant.
So,
Alice doesn't see things changing with
time. Everything stays the same. She
just sees a horizon around her, and that
horizon stays at a fixed distance from
her.
So, would she be seeing the projection
of all things in the past be projected
onto that horizon space? Cuz they'll
never go away, right? Right.
They'll never go away, but she sees it
harder and harder to see them, because
they get red-shifted.
Right.
Now, that doesn't take into account the
Hawking radiation coming from the
horizon, but
but
what you say is right there.
Right.
Okay. So,
assuming that we don't pass through each
other's horizons, we'll meet here next
week.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.